His name is Jan.
I do not know him.
He's from the rig.
You know we do not favor
matrimony with outsiders.
Can you even tell us
what matrimony is?
It's when two people
are joined in God.
Do you really believe
you're capable...
of bearing the responsibility not only
for your own marriage in God...
but also another's?
I know I am.
Can you think of anything
of real value...
that the outsiders
have brought with them?
Their music.
Out you go, Bess McNeill,
and be seated.
♪ Forgot my six-string razor ♪
♪ And hit the sky ♪
♪ Halfway to Memphis
before I realized ♪
♪ Well, I rang the information ♪
♪ My ax was cold ♪
♪ They said she rides a train
to Oriole ♪
♪ Now it's a mighty long way
down the dusty ♪
Bess.
- Bess, don't be silly. You'll ruin your...
- He's late.
All right, but at least he's coming.
Get this on then.
You're gonna ruin your dress.
He's late.
You're being silly. Come on.
- Come on.
- No.
Bess, get your coat on.
- Come on. Don't ruin it. It's a good day.
- No.
You're not supposed to see him.
You know that.
Bess, you're gonna ruin your...
Bess!
You're late!
Come on.
Get in.
Hey!
Break out the bottle!
Come on.
It's my wedding.
Will you please be upstanding
for the bride?
♪ The Lord's my shepherd ♪
♪ I'll not want ♪
♪ He makes me down to lie ♪
♪ In pastures green ♪
♪ He leadeth me ♪
♪ The quiet waters by ♪
As we stand in thy presence today
in thy house...
we worship thee...
as the author of
every good and perfect gift.
Christ loved the church...
and gave himself for her.
We should love Christ
and give ourselves to him.
If it is not too inappropriate...
may I say that you, Bess...
have shown that love
and that commitment in your own life.
It is not once or twice...
that you have been
in this building...
giving your time and effort
to cleaning it.
I know that
you have done that...
not so as to be well
thought of here on earth...
but out of your love
for God in heaven.
Congratulations.
Great sermon, Father.
Ring the bells then.
Our church has no bells.
It's not too fun, is it?
- Oh!
- Hey!
- Whoo-hoo-hoo!
Great.
This is Dodo.
Oh, the sister-in-law.
We haven't really met, have we?
No. But everything happened so quickly.
What makes you say that?
I just mean...
Well, it did, didn't it?
Are you not happy for me?
Of course I am.
Come on, Terry.
- Whoo-hoo-hoo! Hey!
- Yee-ha!
Hey, hey, hey!
Yee-ha!
Get along, little dogie!
Bess.
Yeah.
Dear Bess...
I've known you for six years...
and I can definitely say...
you have the biggest heart
of anyone I've ever met.
It wasn't easy for me here
when I married Sam...
but you welcomed me instantly...
and I won't ever forget that.
Your generosity knows no bounds...
like the time when
you lent Jack a bike...
because his was broken, only it was mine,
and I had to walk to work.
I was furious with you then...
but I regret that now...
because it's your spirit.
You'd give anything to anyone.
When Sam died,
I lost a husband and you, a brother.
We saw each other through that...
and promised to look after
one another.
You are the reason... Sorry.
You are the reason I have stayed
when I almost gave up in this cold place.
And now your warmth...
has embraced another outsider.
His name is Jan...
and I don't know much about him...
but I'll accept his right to be here...
because of you, Bess.
If he doesn't take care of you and give you
everything you need, I'll kill him.
Thank you...
for all you've given me, Bess.
I love you very much.
Have me now.
What, here?
Maybe you wanted
something more romantic.
This is lovely.
Are you sure?
No, have me.
What do I do?
You okay?
You've got blood on your dress.
Shall I go down and wait for you?
You okay?
Hi.
Whoo, whoo, whoo, whoo!
Yee-ha!
Take care of yourself.
Get her now, Jan.
Whoo!
Yeah!
- Whoo, whoo, whoo, whoo!
- Yeah!
Go get her, Jan!
Whoo! Whoo, whoo!
♪ Every day I spend my time ♪
♪ Drinkin' wine, feelin' fine ♪
♪ Waitin' here to find the sign ♪
♪ That I can understand ♪
♪ Yes, I am ♪
♪ In the days between the hours ♪
♪ Ivory towers, bloody flowers ♪
♪ Push their heads into the air ♪
♪ I don't care if I ever know ♪
♪ There I go ♪
♪ Don't push your love too far ♪
I can't get this fucker open.
Shit.
What's so funny?
How could you take it?
How could keep away
from the boys?
I waited for you.
No, don't laugh.
Yeah.
But you must have been lonely.
Who did you talk to?
I thank you
for the greatest gift of all...
the gift of love.
I thank you for Jan.
I'm so lucky to have been
given these gifts.
But remember to be
a good girl, Bess...
for you know I giveth,
and I taketh away.
What? I didn't mean it like that.
Yes. I'll be good.
I'll be really, really good.
Thank you.
What did you say?
Fly...
away!
- Hello, Jan.
- Hello.
- Bess.
Why don't you have
any church bells?
We do not need bells in our church
to worship God.
I like church bells.
Let's put them back again.
Have fun.
But now, friends...
things have become very different.
It hurts me to have to say it...
but there appears to be
those in the church...
who are prepared
to cling to the world...
instead of fleeing from it.
But those to whom I refer...
will know what I am speaking about.
It grieves my heart.
And I know there are others
who feel just the same.
Amen.
Mr. Donald John Beaton,
will you rise and address the question?
Thank you, Lord,
for this day you have blessed us with.
It's stupid that only men
can talk in the service.
Hold your tongue, woman.
Lassie! It's Lassie!
It is Lassie!
I know it.
Lassie! Oh, Lassie!
Oh, welcome home!
They're burying Anthony now.
Go and listen to the minister.
Go on.
Yeah, you can do that if you want.
Men are allowed at funerals.
Go on.
Anthony Dod Mantle, who has been...
Anthony Dod Mantle,
you are a sinner...
and you deserve
your place in hell.
Hmm.
The minister said
he would go to hell.
Did he say that?
Bloody cheerful.
Well, Anthony will go to hell.
Everyone knows that.
You do realize that I will have to
go back soon, don't you?
You knew it all the time.
Lord, we are unworthy
of the least of all thy mercies.
We thank thee for this food.
Pardon our sins
for Jesus' sake. Amen.
Amen.
Okay.
When are you going back?
Oh, didn't you know?
Jan's gonna stay at home with me
and quit the rig because we're so happy.
Oh, Bess. Come on.
I wish I could.
I will not have that kind of
behavior in my house.
I'm sorry, Mother.
I'm sorry.
If you cannot control your moods,
it's the hospital again for you, my girl.
- I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
- Why should you be any different?
Every woman round here
has to learn to be alone...
when their man's away at sea
or on the oil rigs.
Even you can learn
how to endure.
I don't even know
who you are.
I don't know
anything about you.
And quite frankly...
I'm sorry... I'm sorry to say this,
but I don't trust you.
She's...
She's very susceptible...
and you could get her to...
You could get her to do
anything you wanted.
No, I don't think so.
How am I supposed to
look out for her now?
What do you wanna do?
Keep her here?
- Locked up for the rest of her life?
- She hasn't got the strength.
- She's stronger than you and me.
- You don't understand, do you?
- She's not right in the head.
- Come on. She just wants it all.
What's this?
Hmm?
What?
What's that?
It's a present.
- Can I open it?
- Yeah, sure. Open it.
Nice colors, aren't they?
Very cheerful.
It's open.
- Just waiting for you, bud.
- Please.
Yeah, that's fine.
Do you want a little snort?
Look at you.
Bess.
Hey. Hey.
Come, come, come, come.
Okay.
All right? Come on.
It's okay.
Okay.
- Whoo!
Watch your head.
Okay?
It's just a couple of months.
Good-bye!
No!
Bess!
Don't leave!
Bess.
You'll be all right.
You'll be all right here.
Okay?
You'll be all right.
You all right?
You okay?
Oh, dear.
Let's give you one of these.
Come on.
Get one of these down ya.
Come on, darling.
Take one of these. That's it.
Pop it in your mouth.
Swallow.
♪ Who would be a poor man ♪
♪ A beggar man, a thief ♪
♪ If he had a rich man
in his hand? ♪
♪ And who would
steal the candy ♪
♪ From a laughing baby's mouth ♪
♪ If he could take it
from the money man? ♪
♪ Cross-eyed Mary ♪
♪ Goes jumping in again ♪
♪ She signs no contract ♪
♪ But she always
plays the game ♪
♪ She dines
in Hampstead Village ♪
You are guilty
of selfishness, Bess.
You didn't even consider
for one second...
how painful
it must have been for him.
You put your own feelings
before everyone else's.
I can't see that you love him
when you behave like that.
Now you must promise
to be a good girl, Bess.
I promise to be a good girl.
I'm sorry for the way
I behaved, Mother.
That's all right, Bessie.
Mother, would it be okay if I
came home for a bit while Jan's away?
Of course it would, Bessie.
Okay.
Get on it.
A little bit of this shit.
Mmm!
Oh, shit.
- Nice.
- Huh?
You know the waves are...
Jesus Christ.
What the fuck's wrong with you?
Just piss.
Just give me one.
Just wait.
- Now, you know, there's some nice...
- Shit.
- Sorry, guys.
- Just throw the goddamn radio away.
You can't get anything
in here anyhow.
You and your fucking radio.
No! Fuck!
- Geez!
- Come on. Dance. Dance.
Yee-ha! Yee-ha! Yee-ha!
Yee-ha!
Fire!
What? Oh!
- Ah!
- Shit.
Whoo, whoo!
Whoo, whoo, whoo!
- Hey!
- Toro, toro, toro!
Didn't he say he'd call?
Do you want me to wait with you?
Yes, please.
Where the fuck
is the second shift?
I got a phone call to make.
I gotta go to the hospital.
- Are you cold?
- No.
No?
You all right?
Don't wait too long, will ya?
Oh, shit.
Pim, I gotta make a phone call.
Get out of here.
Hello?
Oh, uh, is Bess there?
One moment.
Bess. Bess.
- Is that you, Bess?
- Hi.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I couldn't get to the phone earlier.
That's okay.
Well, don't you
love me anymore?
Oh.
Of course I do.
Say so then.
I'd made up my mind not to.
Everyone says that...
I love you too much, and...
if you found out
how much I loved you...
you might get upset...
because we're not
together right now.
Oh, Bess, never stop
saying you love me. You hear?
- Yes.
- No matter what anybody says.
Yes.
Say it then.
I love you so much.
I love you too.
I can hear you breathing.
Can you hear me?
♪ Take me on a roller coaster ♪
♪ Take me for an airplane ride ♪
♪ Take me for a six-day wonder ♪
♪ But don't throw
my pride aside, besides ♪
♪ What's real
and make-believe? ♪
♪ Baby Jane's in Acapulco ♪
What are you thinking?
That you're here.
- What are you doing?
- Mmm.
Uh...
I'm touching your arms...
and your chest...
and your tummy...
and...
your prick.
You're so huge.
Jan will be home
in 10 days for a week.
Pardon?
Jan will be home
in 10 days for a week.
Pits?
- Hi.
- What are you doing here?
Where's Jan?
I'm the only one back.
Hurt my wrist.
- They sent me home.
- Oh.
He sends his love.
- How long have you got off now?
- Well, only three days.
- Oh.
- Yeah.
You know me. Ha.
I'm back. Oh, sorry.
How long has she been asleep?
What's the matter with you?
Cat got your tongue?
Oh.
Have you taken my calendar?
What?
- Have you taken my calendar?
- No, I have not.
What would I want
with your calendar?
Don't be ridiculous.
- You've taken it.
- I have not taken it.
- Yes, you have.
- I don't know what you're talking about.
What calendar?
Where is it?
Bess, you've got to stop
all this, you know.
You've got to go on living
when he isn't here.
I mean, he's not dead. You're not dead.
You know what I mean?
- Give it to me.
- You just... You've got to stop it.
Shh.
- It's all right. Nothing. Go back to sleep.
- What's going on?
- It's all right. It's all right.
- Was that Bess?
- No, it's okay.
- Bit of hysterics.
No, no. It's all right.
I'll sort it out.
- We're not to have this carry-on in the house.
- I know.
- Just stay where you are. Go back to sleep.
- It's terrible.
Bess McNeill...
for many years
you've prayed for love.
Shall I take it away
from you again?
Is that what you want?
Oh. No.
I'm still grateful for love.
What do you want then?
I pray for Jan to come home.
He will be coming home
in 10 days.
You must learn to endure.
You know that.
I can't wait.
This is unlike you, Bess.
Out there, there are people
who need Jan and his work.
What about them?
They don't matter.
Nothing else matters.
I just want Jan home again.
I pray to you.
Oh, please,
won't you send him home?
Are you sure
that's what you want?
Yes.
Blow out!
- Hey! Get away! Blow out!
- Terry!
Terry!
Terry? Terry!
Terry! Terry!
Terry!
Watch out!
Jan!
- Go get... Call a medic!
- Medic!
I don't know what kind of condition.
I think it's very serious though.
I don't know
what on earth...
It's Jan. There's been
an accident on the rig.
Jan, can you hear me?
Oh.
What are you doing?
I'm holding your hand.
Don't touch me.
- Don't touch me!
- Jan, relax. Just take...
Sit down here. Okay?
That's it. That's it.
You all right? You all right?
Shh. Deep breath.
Come on.
Hello. Talk to me, darling.
Talk to me.
Come on. Oh, come on.
It's all right.
It's gonna be all right.
Uh, they're gonna operate
straightaway.
It'll be a few hours,
so I think we better wait...
Bess.
Bess, you can't go in there.
- I want to be with him.
- It's not allowed.
I know you do.
I know, but come on. Come with me.
No, I want to see him
all the time.
Bess, it's not a good idea.
- Come on.
- Bess. Bess. Please.
You can't stay here.
It's just not possible.
Bess.
Can I have a word with you?
Stay there, all right?
Don't move.
I want you to pray with me.
- What?
- Please.
Dear God...
we pray that you will
hold your hand over Jan...
and not let him die.
Amen.
Mrs. Nyman,
will you please come with me?
Will he live?
We have stabilized
your husband's condition for the time being.
Will he live?
Yes. Yes, Bess.
He will live.
Your husband suffered
very serious injuries.
Life shouldn't always
be preserved at any cost.
What do you mean?
Um, well, the doctor means,
Bess, that...
um, sometimes...
in some cases,
when life isn't worth living...
then it may be better to die.
You don't know Jan...
or you could not
say such a thing.
Your husband
may never walk again.
We think he'll be
completely paralyzed.
But he'll live.
Yes.
He will live, it seems.
Father...
are you there?
Are you still there?
Of course I am, Bess.
You know that.
What's happening?
You wanted Jan home.
I've changed my mind.
Why... Why did I ask for that?
Because you're
a stupid little girl, Bess.
I had to test you.
Your love for Jan
has been put to the test.
Thank you for not letting him die.
You're welcome, Bess.
♪ She said there is no reason ♪
♪ And the truth
is plain to see ♪
♪ But I wandered
through my playing cards ♪
♪ And would not let her be ♪
♪ One of 16 vestal virgins ♪
♪ Who were leaving for the coast ♪
♪ And although my eyes were open ♪
♪ They might just as well
have been closed ♪
♪ And so it was ♪
And I would say to you...
that if there is
one of these commandments...
which you do not love...
and do not obey...
you have no place
at the Lord's table.
- When did you get back?
- I came back with Jan.
Oh. It's nice to see you.
- Ta-da!
- Surf's up!
- Hi.
- Hi, guys.
- How you doing, bud?
- I'm fine. How are you?
Okay.
Did you find anything?
Gas. Nothing really.
Guess what now.
We're heading up north.
- Well, north, that's good.
- That's where you always said the oil was.
What are you doing here anyway?
We're meant to be out drilling.
I...
just felt like
putting my feet up for a while.
Wouldn't trust you two guys
out there alone.
Well, my...
my arms aren't okay, so...
I'm not thirsty anyway.
Bullshit!
Here. Come on.
Come on.
Oh, man. Sorry.
- Oh, man. Sorry.
- Thank you.
Thank you.
I'm not really supposed
to have any visitors, so...
We really don't have
the time either.
- Okay.
- You take care of yourself, huh?
- Take care.
Get well soon.
See you, guys.
Will you do something for me?
Yes?
The next time you come,
could you wear something more...
more loose?
So I, uh...
So I won't have to see your body.
Bess, you'll have to go now,
'cause Jan needs to rest.
All right?
You shouldn't get him
too overemotional, you know.
It's not good for him.
I'm sorry.
You got to cheer him up.
Is he asleep now?
Well, he should be,
with the amount I've given him.
Would it be all right
if I went and had a look at him?
I love you, Jan.
I love you too, Bess.
You are the love of my life.
Bess.
Where have you been?
I've been to the church.
What, at 2:00 in the morning?
I don't want you
getting ill again...
like you did when Sam died.
- I said I've been to the church.
- It's nothin' to do with the church.
Did you hear what I said?
Did you?
I don't want you to get ill again
like you did when Sam died.
I've had a word with Dr. Richardson.
All right?
And... And he says
he could see you tomorrow.
Oh, can he?
Bess, would you
like to come in?
Dodo said I had to come.
She has this idea
about me treating you.
My predecessor admitted you
a few years ago.
Uh, wh...
why did he do that?
I don't know.
No, nor do I.
You were upset
because your brother had died, and...
now you're upset
because your husband's ill.
Nothing unusual about that.
Am I not going to have some pills?
I'm probably not like your old doctor.
I don't think that people
should be given pills...
just because they do
what's only natural.
Maybe showing what you feel isn't
the done thing from where you come from...
but it's certainly no disease.
What happened on the rig
was my fault.
How come?
I prayed to God to send him home.
Wow.
What powers you possess.
Come on. Do you really... Do you really
believe that you possess such powers?
I know you people
believe a lot about yourselves.
Bess...
perhaps you should do a bit of grieving
for yourself instead of him.
I think you should come and see me
now and again if you feel like it.
I'm sorry.
Oh.
Come on.
Things will pick up
once he gets home again.
♪ Well, she's my woman of gold ♪
♪ And she's not very old,
a-a-ha ♪
♪ Well, she's my woman of gold ♪
♪ And she's not very old, a-a-ha ♪
♪ I don't mean to be bold,
but may I hold your hand? ♪
♪ Well, she ain't no witch ♪
♪ And I love the way she twitch,
a-a-ha ♪
♪ Well, she ain't no witch ♪
♪ And I love the way she twitch
a-a-ha ♪
♪ Happy birthday to you ♪
♪ Squashed tomatoes and stew ♪
♪ You look like a monkey ♪
♪ And we thought it was you ♪
Look at that.
Special.
Shall I open your present?
Yes.
- Lovely.
- Present.
Can you see all right?
What is it?
Wait and see.
I don't believe it.
Where did you get that?
- I got it in a shop.
- That is...
That is
the stupidest thing I've ever seen.
Oh, look.
It's not doing anything now.
All right.
Go on. Well, go on.
That is just terrible.
How daft that is. Completely daft.
Just like...
Happy birthday, Jan.
Thank you.
I'll see you later.
Do you like it?
Oh, yes. It's...
It's w... It's nice.
I'll give you your pill.
Okay?
Oh. One more drink.
Yeah. It went down.
Thank you.
Happy birthday.
I'm finished, Bess.
No.
You could take a lover
without anybody noticing.
But you can't divorce me.
They'd never let you.
- Bess.
- No. No.
Is that what you think I want?
You cripple!
You must make up with him.
A husband and wife have to be able
to talk to each other.
He's the one who is helpless...
and you're the one
who must show you're strong.
Go to him, and tell him
you are sorry you were angry.
You have God.
You have the strength
your life in God has bestowed upon you.
And that is a strength
he does not possess.
Oh, no.
Come on.
Come on, love.
Be all right.
That's it. Come on. That's it.
That's it.
It's all right, all right, all right.
Don't know what she's thinking of...
going off leaving you like this.
You must admit that she was...
she was happy when we got married.
She blossomed...
didn't she?
I can't just lie here.
I can't even make love to her.
She's gotta get out of here.
She's gotta get on with life.
Help me set her free.
She'd do anything for you, Jan.
You know that.
She doesn't care
anything about herself.
But she'd do anything for you.
Just to see a smile on your face.
Do you understand me?
Yeah.
Right.
Thanks for telling me.
No trouble.
Do you want me to read to you?
Hmm?
Are you all right?
They took him back
to the hospital.
Bess. Bess, what is going on?
- What happened? Is he...
- He went unconscious.
We had to bring him back here.
We can't have him
at home anymore...
not if you're gonna go running off
and leaving him like that.
- I'm sorry.
- Well, it's just not good enough.
I'm not... I'm not even allowed
to kiss him anymore.
Why don't you try listening
to what he says, Bess?
It's up to you.
He hasn't got anyone else.
You could give him the will to live.
It's more than
any doctor could do.
Bess?
I'm sorry.
No, it was my fault.
Come here.
Hi.
Love is a mighty power...
isn't it?
If I'll die...
it will be because
love cannot keep me alive.
But I can hardly remember
what it's like to make love...
and if I forget that, then I'll die.
Remember when I phoned you
from the rig...
and we made love
without being together?
Do you want me to talk to you
like that again? I-I'd love to.
Bess...
I want you to find a man...
to make love to...
and then come back here
and tell me about it.
It will feel like you and me
being together again.
Now, that... that
will keep me alive.
I... I can't.
This morning when I...
when I told you to...
to get a lover...
it wasn't for your sake.
It was for my sake.
Because I don't want to die.
I'm afraid.
You understand?
Yes.
It will be you and me, Bess.
Do it for me.
I...
I can't.
Please?
Bess?
Are you all right?
Sure?
Here you go.
Whoa, whoa, whoa,
whoa, whoa, whoa. Easy.
♪ Suzanne takes you down ♪
♪ To her place
near the river ♪
♪ You can hear
the boats go by ♪
♪ You can spend the night
beside her ♪
♪ And you know
that she's half crazy ♪
♪ But that's why
you want to be there ♪
♪ And she feeds you
tea and oranges ♪
♪ That come
all the way from China ♪
♪ And just when
you mean to tell her ♪
♪ That you have
no love to give her ♪
♪ Then she gets you
on her wavelength ♪
♪ And she lets
the river answer ♪
♪ That you've always
been her lover ♪
You certainly needed
some shut-eye.
I put your rose in a vase.
Think it's perked up a bit.
You should think
of yourself a bit too.
Go out.
Go dancing.
I've seen you dance.
You like to dance.
Where is Jan?
There's nothing
you can do in here.
Don't let him die.
And why shouldn't I let him die?
I love him.
So you keep saying,
but I don't see it.
There's nothing I can do.
There's nothing at all.
Prove to me that you love him...
and then I'll let him live.
I've come to dance.
It's great. You're great. Great movement.
But maybe you could talk to me?
♪ And love lies bleeding in my hand ♪
♪ Oh, it kills me to think of you ♪
♪ With another man ♪
Bess, stop dancing.
Talk to me.
♪ But my guitar couldn't hold you,
so I split the band ♪
- Bess.
- ♪ Love lies bleeding ♪
- Talk to me.
- ♪ In my hand ♪
Give me five minutes.
You can touch me now.
You can have me now.
Bess, listen to me.
We're not going to make love.
Now put your clothes back on.
Don't you want me?
Don't you like me?
You said that you liked me.
Yes, Bess, I like you.
Now put your clothes on.
You don't understand.
I'll...
I'll be good to you and...
I want us to make love.
Listen, um, Bess...
if you want to talk to me...
we can meet at the hospital,
all right?
Now please just...
put your clothes on, Bess.
Please. I don't know
what to do with you.
All right now, just...
put your clothes on, Bess,
and go home.
No.
I'm lying on my back...
all naked...
and...
he comes in and he sees me...
he kisses my breasts.
Um...
and he enters me...
um...
and...
he's making love to me...
gently...
and...
he's coming.
It was Dr. Richardson.
Hi.
- Hi, Bess.
Where you going then?
Uh, I've got to go
to the church.
Oh.
Jan, we're gonna take you
off the respirator for five minutes...
to exercise your lungs a little bit
and see how you are.
So just relax and take it easy.
Okay, start to breathe
by yourself now, Jan.
Just take very deep breaths.
Slowly.
That's it.
And again.
Very good.
Deep breaths.
That's it.
Bess.
Yes?
What are you doing on this bus?
Which bus, Jan?
Come to me.
Come.
I'm here.
I'm here in the back.
Yes?
- In the back of the bus.
- Yes.
Come.
Dodo?
- Dodo.
- Hang on.
Jan.
Go and get Dr. Richardson.
I'm gonna put you back
on the respirator now, Jan.
Jan, can you hear me?
Are you awake?
Talk to me.
Hi, Bess.
I'd like to have a chat with you.
- Bess?
- Mmm.
This is my bus.
Forgive me, Father.
I have sinned.
Mary Magdalene sinned...
and she's among
my dearly beloved.
I go to the back of the bus...
and you're there.
And you're so huge...
that you're almost bursting
out of your pants.
And I undo your fly...
and I touch you.
I'm touching your prick.
Have you been in to see Jan?
- How is he?
- Better.
- He's better?
- Just a bit.
Hey, Bess, it looks like your prayers
have been answered.
We've been able to take him
off the respirator.
Good news, isn't it?
Do you think...
that we turn to different people...
when we get close to the edge?
And that we, um...
we turn bad...
when we're going to die?
You're not going to die.
I know you're not.
I promise you.
♪ When are you gonna come down? ♪
♪ When are you going to land? ♪
♪ I should have stayed on the farm ♪
♪ I should have listened
to my old man ♪
♪ You know you can't
hold me forever ♪
♪ I didn't sign up with you ♪
♪ I'm not a present
for your friends to open ♪
♪ This boy's too young
to be singing ♪
♪ The blues ♪
Ooh, look.
Here you go.
Hey, hey, girlies!
We found some shroomies!
Don't get your hopes up
too high, will you?
Dr. Richardson says that
Jan could get worse again.
I'm the one
who saved his life.
I can save it again.
Bess. What are you
talking about?
I told Jan stories.
Stories about love.
That was almost like
being together, him and me.
You see, love can save Jan.
He must not forget about love.
He told me that.
He tells me what to do.
Bess, I'm glad
that you listen to Jan...
but don't let him gain
too much power over you.
Sickness is a mighty power.
You know that.
I've saved Jan.
Don't talk like that.
It's stupid!
You always said
that I wasn't stupid.
Well, you're stupid
if you say things like that.
Why are you saying
I'm stupid now?
Because I can see
that you're disappearing...
into a world of make-believe...
and it worries me.
I used to go mad when people
called you stupid, but...
you are stupid!
We're gonna put a drain in this afternoon.
Just wait and see.
It'll be much easier to get through to him.
Don't worry.
It's a very minor operation.
Are you trying to make me feel guilty?
What makes you say that?
I think she's trying
to make me feel guilty.
Come here.
You look fucking awful.
Why do you dress like that?
You dress like a widow.
I'm not even dead yet.
Maybe you wish I was.
No! No, no.
You haven't done
what I asked you to.
I have!
I asked you to be with a man.
I... I have done that.
You call that being with a man?
I call it a joke.
I love you.
I don't love some other man.
Prove it.
Bess.
What is going on?
Are you sleeping with other men
to feed his sick fantasies?
He did get better.
No, he did not get better.
That's just the way it goes.
Sometimes he's better, sometimes he's worse.
Nothing to do with what you're doing.
That's all in your mind.
He is my husband...
and God has said
that I must honor him.
Well, if that's what
honoring is all about...
then I must have something wrong.
Well, you don't come
from around here, do you?
No, and I'm glad I don't.
The way the locals talk,
it makes me sick.
But you live here
and you go to the church.
Yes, but that don't mean
I don't look at things me own way.
Why don't you move then?
Your husband's dead.
You know very well
why I don't move.
I don't move because of you.
A woman has to choose
for herself, Bess.
She has to have
a mind of her own.
Now, what you're doing is...
making things worse.
It's... nonsense.
His... His head's full of scars.
He's up to his eyeballs in drugs.
He doesn't know what he's saying.
And he doesn't know.
I'm sorry.
Am I going to go to hell?
Whom do you want to save?
Yourself or Jan?
Bess?
It's been a long time.
Most unlike you.
I must warn you that the Lord
looks with anger upon those who fail him.
You've got to lend me
something to wear.
He's never gonna beat me.
You're low man.
All right, all right.
Hello.
How much, darlin'?
One, two, three.
Thank you.
Okay.
I can't hear the blood pressure.
We have a fibrillation.
Clear.
- Shit.
- No, there's no change.
Okay. Clear.
- Clear again, please.
- Clear.
Come on.
Clear, please.
All right.
Yes. Good.
Good work.
It's okay.
Hi, Bess.
Bess?
Bess.
Think it's time
we had a little chat.
I love you,
no matter what is in your head.
So you didn't have to give Jan
electric shock treatment...
when his heart stopped
in the operation yesterday?
No, we didn't.
It was a perfectly simple operation.
It went very well.
As you know.
I shouldn't have to say that.
You know that very well.
I want a word
with Bess on her own.
Thank you, Dorothy.
I'm not going to ask you
what you've been getting up to...
'cause I don't want
to hear you lie to me.
But as long as you are
living under my roof...
you are to behave like
a decent human being.
I've never lied to you.
Do you understand me?
Yes, Mother.
This is very painful for me.
Your grandfather can no longer
hold his hand over you...
with the elders.
I don't think you realize
what that means.
Have you any idea
what it's like to be cast out?
You will have nothing, Bess.
I have known strong men
and women...
wither away after being cast out.
Now, you are not strong.
You're a feeble girl.
It would kill you, Bess.
I've said enough.
Bess?
Bess.
Could you come down a minute, love?
Dr. Richardson is here.
Hi, Bess.
Hello.
Well, how are you?
Can we sit down?
Mmm.
Bess.
I th... I think you've
got yourself involved...
in something which is
out of your control.
Have I?
Come on, Bess.
You're not a kid anymore.
Look, for Christ's sake, he's...
he's forcing you to get screwed
by every Tom, Dick and Harry.
It's just not you.
I don't make love with them.
I make love with Jan...
and I save him from dying.
Well, I'm sorry, but, you know...
to me he seems more like a dirty old man
who wants to play the Peeping Tom.
Sometimes...
I don't even
have to tell him about it.
Jan and me...
we have a spiritual contact.
God gives everyone
something to be good at.
I've always been stupid...
but I'm good at this.
God gives everyone a talent.
What's Jan's talent?
He is...
He's a great lover.
Well, what's...
what's mine, then?
I don't know.
Haven't you found it yet?
I see.
And what's your talent then, Bess?
Because, um, surely it can't be...
being screwed by men
you've never seen before.
I can believe.
Are you angry now?
Yes, I'm...
Yeah, yeah, yeah,
I am angry...
because you can't see that
he's messing you about.
He's the one who's sick.
Look, what he's
doing to you is sick...
and it's getting
sicker and sicker.
He's becoming more and more of a danger
to you the more the fluid rises in his...
Listen to me, for God's sake!
Do you always get so involved...
in your patients' problems,
Dr. Richardson?
Listen to me, Bess.
I care for you.
I love you, Bess.
You're very special.
Will you move your hands, please.
Dodo.
Will you show
Dr. Richardson out, please?
What's...
What's gonna happen now then, Bess? Um...
Has he told you any more
of the thoughts he's had...
any more services
for you to perform?
Don't come here again.
Oh, he has, has he?
What's it gonna be this time?
What are you gonna give him
to slobber over this time?
Dear Father...
what's going on?
Father? Where are you?
We just don't want to wait
for someone like that.
Hello.
Can you take me
out to the ships?
Can't take you out there.
The other girls wouldn't like it.
They can't do all the ships.
They don't have time.
Maybe not.
Well, what about the big one?
I don't go out to that one anymore.
The girls won't go aboard.
Well, then you can take me,
and no harm done.
How are you feeling, Jan?
Well...
I've felt better.
Yeah. Yeah.
Unfortunately, the periods
in which we can get through to you...
have lately become very rare.
I have to send you back to Glasgow
for a while, I'm afraid.
I don't want any more...
operations.
Of course,
it's entirely up to you, but...
I have to say that your condition
is unlikely to improve without surgery.
Well, if you've made your mind up
on that point...
maybe it's time
to consider other matters.
I mean, we should start thinking
about other people than just you.
Bess?
I'm glad you understand
what I'm driving at.
Your...
Your condition...
has been...
has been very hard on her.
I can't judge why, but she's...
she's suffering from delusions
regarding your condition.
I have to be blunt.
I don't think that seeing you
is good for her.
I guess not.
And I'm convinced that the best thing
we can do for her right now...
is to admit her again.
Get her away?
Yes.
As far away as possible.
Think that's necessary?
Listen, if you don't want surgery...
the indications are that we will enter
a prolonged period...
in which you will be more and more
affected by your condition.
The poorlier you are...
the more detrimental
your influence on Bess.
I've drawn up some papers
giving me the authority to detain her...
under the provisions
of the Mental Health Act.
I'll need your consent.
You're going to section Bess?
It's the only way
I can get her treated.
Tell me, Dr. Richardson.
Does this mean
I will never see her again?
To be realistic, yes.
Just there at the bottom.
You said you wanted to help her.
Come on, Jan.
♪ If you been bad ♪
♪ Lord, I bet you have ♪
♪ And you've not been hit ♪
♪ You've not been hit
by flying lead ♪
♪ You'd better
close your eyes ♪
bow your head ♪
♪ Wait for the ricochet ♪
♪ Ooh-ooh-ooh ♪
How do I get back?
I'll keep an eye out for you.
Hello.
What do you want?
I want that you do it
with the sailor and I watch.
Okay.
It's all right.
- All right. Come here, you.
- No.
There we go. Eh?
Yeah, that's better.
Come on now.
Yeah. That's right.
You like this, eh?
No. Please.
Can I go home now?
No, no.
Can I go home now, please?
- Stay still!
- No, please.
- No, no, please... Please, can I go home?
- Stay still, I said!
Stay still, I said!
Stay... God's sake.
No!
You bitch!
I'm going to shoot you!
- You will?
- I'm gonna shoot you.
You think so?
You don't even know
how to use that thing.
Nobody will believe a hooker!
Because there is only one thing for us,
sinners that we are...
to achieve perfection
in the eyes of God...
through unconditional love
for the word that is written...
for the law.
I don't understand
what you're saying.
How can you love...
a word?
You cannot love words.
You cannot be in love with a word.
You can love another human being.
That's perfection.
No woman speaks here!
Bess McNeill, the kirk session...
- has decided this day...
- No, let me stay here.
that henceforth you shall no longer
have access to this kirk.
- They who know you shall not know you.
- Please let me stay!
Please. No.
Begone, Bess McNeill,
from the house of God!
Hello, Bess. You're...
You're coming with us.
We're going to Glasgow.
Bess, they're going to take you
back into hospital just for a little bit.
It's for your own good.
I want to see Jan.
I want to see my husband.
I know.
But not now, Bess.
It's for your own good, Bess.
Mother can't have me admitted,
not now that I'm married.
Bess, it wasn't Mother
that signed the paper.
It was Jan.
- You liar!
- Come along, Bess.
Jan!
Dodo, how can you do this?
You had a husband too once.
Your love could've saved him,
if only you'd tried.
Jan!
Okay, Bess, let's go.
Oh, fuck.
Ryan. She's no here.
Hello.
Who's a tart?
What you doing?
I can't open the door!
Please.
Mother?
Please, Mother!
Open the door!
Please open the d...
Mother!
I'll be good.
I'll be really, really good.
I'll be really good.
Please help.
Would you please go away?
Stop it! Go away!
You just go away
and leave me!
Who's a tart?
Away with you!
Stop all this racket
outside the house of God.
Go on! On you go!
What's happened?
Bess. Bess?
Bess. Are you all right, love?
Bess? It's Dodo.
Oh, Bess.
Mmm.
Jan is dying.
I-I wasn't to tell you.
- I wasn't to tell you.
- No.
It's good you told me.
I know you love me.
I have to go.
- Is there anything I can do for you?
- No.
Anything at all?
Yes.
I'd like you to go to Jan
and pray for him to be cured...
and to rise from his bed
and walk.
Will you take me to the big ship?
Again?
Are you sure?
Father, why aren't you with me?
I am with you, Bess.
What do you want from me?
Where were you?
Well, don't you think I have other people
who want to talk to me?
Oh, of course.
I hadn't thought of that.
There's this silly little thing
called Bess...
who keeps on wanting me
to talk to her...
so my work's been piling up a bit.
But you're with me now?
Of course I am, Bess.
You know that.
Thank you.
I'm sorry.
Do you need me?
No, no, that's all right.
Stay there.
Bess asked me to pray.
For what?
For Jan's life.
For a miracle.
Yeah, that would be a miracle.
Dear God...
I pray that Jan gets better...
that he rises from his bed
and walks.
Sister McNeill here.
Where's Jan?
I'd like to see him.
No, not now, love.
You're gonna have an operation now.
I want to see him.
Not now.
You need an operation.
No, I've got to see Jan.
Please, Dodo.
All right.
All right, stop.
She wants to see Jan.
I'm gonna take her to see Jan.
Come on. Out the way, for God's sake.
Help me. Come on.
Move, for Christ's sake!
All right. All right.
Here you go.
There you are.
You can see him now, can't you?
How's he...
How's he doing?
He's...
Is he not any better?
No. No, he's not.
Oh.
I thought he might be better now.
Hmm.
Maybe I was wrong after all.
Okay, let's get her inside.
- Take those.
- Yeah.
Okay.
Take care. Let's go.
One, two, three.
There we go.
Okay.
It's all right, love.
Hi, Bess. Do you know me?
Pulse, 90.
Okay.
- What happened? Do you know?
- No.
- Pressure, 100.
- Okay.
- Blood pressure?
- 100.
You'll be all right, love.
You'll be all right.
I'm just gonna have a look
at her back. There we go.
Okay. Give me the scissors.
- Yes.
- All right.
Mother.
Here she is.
Oh, Bessie.
Bess.
I'm sorry that I could not
be good, Mother.
It's all right, Bessie.
Your grandfather's...
sorry he couldn't come.
Will you tell him
that I love him?
I'm glad...
that you came, Mother.
Blood pressure?
Yeah.
- It's going down.
- Right.
- Two units now. Two units. Immediately.
- Two units.
We're just gonna lower you down a bit now.
All right, love?
Take her head.
There we go.
- That was easy, wasn't it?
- Yeah.
Yeah. Gonna be all right.
Oh, Do...
Dodo, h-hold me.
Yeah, I'm holding you.
- It's all right, love. I'm here. I'm here.
- I'm... I'm afraid.
I know... I know you are.
Jan?
Jan.
Shh, now. Shush.
I'm frightened.
It's...
It's all wrong.
No pulse.
Bess?
Stand clear. Stand clear.
Clear! Clear!
It's gonna be all right.
That's a good girl.
Come on.
- Okay, you can stop now.
- Wh-Wh... What do you mean?
She's gone, Dodo. She's gone.
She's gone.
- No.
- She's gone.
No.
Bess. Bess.
Listen to me.
I'm sorry.
I'm... I'm sorry.
Dodo.
Come on.
Come on, Dodo. Let's go.
♪ It's a god-awful small affair ♪
♪ To the girl
with the mousy hair ♪
♪ But her mummy
is yelling no ♪
♪ And her daddy
has told her to go ♪
♪ But her friend
is nowhere to be seen ♪
♪ Now she walks
through her sunken dream ♪
♪ To the seat
with the clearest view ♪
♪ And she's hooked
to the silver screen ♪
♪ But the film
is a saddening bore ♪
♪ 'Cause she's lived it
ten times or more ♪
♪ She could spit
in the eyes of fools ♪
♪ As they ask her
to focus on ♪
♪ Sailors ♪
♪ Fighting in the dance hall ♪
♪ Oh, man,
look at those cavemen go ♪
♪ It's the freakiest show ♪
♪ Take a look at the lawman ♪
♪ Beating up the wrong guy ♪
♪ Oh, man,
wonder if he'll ever know ♪
♪ He's in the best-selling show ♪
♪ Is there life on Mars? ♪
You have described
the deceased as...
"an immature, unstable person...
"a person who, due to the trauma
of her husband's illness...
"gave way in obsessive fashion...
"to an exaggerated,
perverse form of sexuality."
Would you like to clarify that
to the inquiry?
Uh, that's what I wrote.
Yes, that's...
that's what it says.
Can I have a glass of water, please?
Get Dr. Richardson
a glass of water.
Thank you.
Listen, man,
you had the deceased in your care.
The court would like
to hear the medical facts.
If... If you'd, um...
If you were to ask me
again to write...
um...
the conclusion, then...
in-instead of writing "neurotic"...
or, um, "psychotic"...
uh, I might...
just, um...
use a word like...
"good."
Good?
Yes.
You wish the records
of this court...
to state that
in your medical opinion...
the deceased was suffering
from being good?
Perhaps this was the psychological defect
that led to her death.
Is that what we shall write,
Dr. Richardson?
No. Of course not.
Very well then.
Perhaps we should stick to your
original statement then, Doctor?
Yes.
I think that everything there is to say
about Bess McNeill...
has been said already.
We have agreed
to sanction her burial...
but there can be
no funeral service.
The fact that some of us knew
the deceased girl well...
cannot be allowed to influence...
the form of her burial.
Bess McNeill's funeral
must be the same...
as anyone else of her kind.
The body will be released
by the authorities sometime this week.
I have obtained permission
from the elders to bury Bess...
but...
I cannot deviate from the principles
that apply to funerals here.
I must say about Bess
what must be said.
Okay, come on.
Where's Jan?
Has he gone down there yet?
Don't know. No.
- Have you seen Jan?
- No.
Bess McNeill,
you are a sinner...
and for your sins
you are consigned to hell.
Not one of you...
has the right
to consign Bess to hell.
Terry, it's time.
Let's do it.
Get up, for Christ's sake!
Come on, man.
Come on.
Take good care of her.
Come on, Jan.
You gotta let her go.
Bess!
Jan.
- Jan. Hey.
- What's the matter?
Come on. Come on.
I want to show you something.
- You're not gonna believe it.
- What?
Come on.
- Let me go. Please.
- Here. Let's go.
Pim!
Pim, come on!
You're not gonna believe it.
Hey, Pim.
Come on and check this out.
Check this thing out, man.
Do you see anything?
There's nothing out there.
I've tried all the fucking ranges,
and there's nothing there.
I just wanted to be sure.
Come on!